let's move now to process scheduling we
have a dedicated lecture about
scheduling so this is just a
simple introduction here so
we said that the context switch needs to
be fast
this implies that when we need to decide
what is the next
process that should run we should be
efficient
now how efficient the operating system
is
depends on the data structures that it
uses
to maintain the information about the
processes or the process control blocks
here you have a first example of the
tradeoffs I mentioned between space and
time complexity
you can keep everything in a single data
structure
that is potentially simple it reduces
space complexity but then it's not
optimal for time complexity if you keep
everything inside
the same data structure you might need
to traverse
the entire data structure to find out
which is the next program that you want
to run
so the operating system does something
smarter than this
it actually keeps different queues
in which it stores the process control
blocks
one queue is the queue of processes that
are ready
or process control
blocks that refer to processes that are
ready and then there are different
queues depending on the input output
device
okay so you can have a queue that is
containing only the process control
blocks
of processes that are waiting for the
disk
and to say that one process
changes its state from waiting to ready
could actually mean that the process
control block of that process
is removed from the queue that refers to
a disk unit and it's added back to the
queue of the ready processes
this organization helps in reducing the
context switch time
because if you want to know what is the
next ready process to run
you don't need to check among all the
process control blocks you have
but you can just pick the next in the
queue of the process control blocks that
are about ready processes
so this is the let's say
life cycle of the process once it starts
it gets into the ready queue
and it gets some CPU time at a certain
point
it might just terminate or
some other things could happen there can
be a request
and then it will go in the queue of
some I/O device until
the I/O is done
it might be that it's the time slice
that is given expires the operating
system
might say each program runs
for 10 milliseconds there is always this
clock ticking and creating interrupts
let's say every second so sometimes the
operating system might wake up
and check how much time it does
let a certain process run and then put
it back to the ready queue we will see
that processes can
fork a child or better said
they can create other processes
and this could be a reason why you stop
running this process and you start
running
a different one or they could be
just waiting for an interrupt
in which they will stay in this
waiting state until they get
an interrupt and then they will go back
to the ready queue
now you have both short term schedulers
and long term
schedulers as the name suggests the
short time
scheduler selects the process that
should be executed next
so the process that should get the CPU
and this is maybe the only
scheduler you ever for sure the
scheduler you need because it's the one
taking decision immediately about what
to run next
you can also have long-term
schedulers so it might be that
there are
processes that need to be put to sleep
because there are not enough resources
we would see this thing in a
certain number of lectures when we talk
about virtual memory
okay so these are let's say taking
decision on a larger
time frame than the short term schedules